This sound,
هذا الصوت
this smell,
هذه الرائحة
this sight
هذا المنظر
all remind me of the campfires of my childhood,
كلها تأخذني بالذاكرة إلى تحلقنا حول النار في زمن الطفولة
when anyone could become a storyteller in front of the dancing flames.
عندما يصبح كل منا قاص أمام اللهب المتراقص
There was this wondrous ending
كانت هناك تلك النهاية العجيبة
when people and fire fell asleep almost in unison.
عندما ينام الناس وتخمد النار في تناغم رائع
It was dreaming time.
كان ذلك زمان الأحلام.
Now my story has a lot to do with dreaming,
لقصتي العديد من الجوانب المتعلقة بالأحلام،
although I'm known to make my dreams come true.
وذلك على الرغم من أني معروف بتحقيق أحلامي.
Last year, I created a one-man show.
في السنة الماضية، قدمت عرضا منفردا
For an hour and a half I shared with the audience
لساعة ونصف، تشاركت مع الجمهور
a lifetime of creativity,
قصة رحلة عمر من الابداع
how I pursue perfection, how I cheat the impossible.
كيف لاحقت الكمال، وكيف خدعت المستحيل.
And then TED challenged me:
وحينها، تحداني TED :
"Philippe, can you shrink this lifetime to 18 minutes?"
"فيليب، هل يمكنك اختصار رحلة الحياة هذه في 18 دقيقة؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Eighteen minutes, clearly impossible.
ثماني عشرة دقيقة!! بالطبع يستحيل
But here I am.
ولكن، ها أنا ذا
One solution was to rehearse a machine gun delivery
أحد الحلول كان بمحاكاة المدفع الرشاش
in which every syllable, every second will have its importance
حيث لكل مقطع صوتي، ولكل ثانية أهميتها
and hope to God the audience will be able to follow me.
ومن ثم أتمنى من الله أن الجمهور يستطيع مجاراتي.
No, no, no.
كلا، كلا، كلا
No, the best way for me to start
كلا، أفضل طريق بالنسبة لي كي أبدأ
is to pay my respects to the gods of creativity.
هي أن أمجد الله الخالق المبدع.
So please join me for a minute of silence.
لذا فأرجو منكم أن تنضموا إلي في دقيقة صمت
Okay, I cheated, it was a mere 20 seconds.
حسنا، لقد غششت، بالكاد هي 20 ثانية
But hey, we're on TED time.
ولكن انتبهوا، نحن في حضرة TED وفي وقتهم
When I was six years old,
عندما كنت في السادسة من عمري
I fell in love with magic.
أغرمت بالسحر
For Christmas I got a magic box
للعيد، تحصلت على صندوق سحري
and a very old book on card manipulation.
ومعه كتاب قديم في التلاعب بالورق - الكوتشينة
Somehow I was more interested in pure manipulation
بطريقة ما، كنت مهتما بالتلاعب المحض
than in all the silly little tricks in the box.
أكثر من أي خدع سخيفة في ذلك الصندوق
So I looked in the book for the most difficult move,
لذا ألقيت نظرة على الكتاب بحثا عن أصعب الخدع
and it was this.
وهذه هي
Now I'm not supposed to share that with you,
ليس من المفترض أن أشاركم هذا
but I have to show you the card is hidden in the back of the hand.
ولكني سأريكم أن الورق مخفي في الجهة الخلفية من اليد
Now that manipulation
هذه الخدعة
was broken down into seven moves
مقسمة إلى سبع حركات
described over seven pages.
وصفت في سبع صفحات
One, two, three,
واحد، اثنان، ثلاثة
four, five, six and seven.
أربعة، خمسة، ستة، سبعة
And let me show you something else.
دعوني أريكم شيئا آخر
The cards were bigger than my hands.
كان الورق أكبر من يداي
Two months later, six years old,
بعد شهرين، ومازلت ابن السادسة
I'm able to do one, two, three, four, five, six, seven.
كان في استطاعتي أن أفعل: واحد، اثنان، ثلاثة، أربعة، خمسة، ستة، سبعة
And I go to see a famous magician
وذهبت لأرى ساحرا مشهورا
and proudly ask him, "Well what do you think?"
وبكل الفخر سألته "حسنا، ما رأيك؟"
Six years old.
ابن الست سنوات
The magician looked at me and said, "This is a disaster.
نظر إلي وقال: "هذه كارثة
You cannot do that in two seconds
لايمكنك أن تؤدي هذه الحركة في ثانيتين
and have a minuscule part of the card showing.
وأيضا ان تترك جزءا من الورق بارزا
For the move to be professional, it has to be less than one second
يجب أن تؤدي الخدعة في أقل من ثانية حتى تكون محترفا
and it has to be perfect."
ويجب أن تكون متقنة."
Two years later, one -- zoop.
سنتين لاحقتين، واحد .. زوب
And I'm not cheating. It's in the back. It's perfect.
وأنا لا أخادع، إنها في الخلف، إنها متقنة
Passion is the motto
الشغف
of all my actions.
هو الشعار لكل أفعالي.
As I'm studying magic,
وبينما كنت أدرس السحر
juggling is mentioned repeatedly
ذكرت أمامي كلمة التلاعب مرارا
as a great way to acquire dexterity and coordination.
كطريقة لاكتساب الخفة والتناسق في الحركة
Now I had long admired how fast and fluidly
الآن أصبحت معجبا بالسرعة والسلاسة
jugglers make objects fly.
التي يجعل المتلاعبون الأشياء بها تتطاير
So that's it. I'm 14; I'm becoming a juggler.
إذن، هذا هو.. أصبحت في الرابعة عشرة من عمري، سأصبح لاعب خفة - بهلوان
I befriend a young juggler in a juggling troupe,
صاحبت لاعب خفة في إحدى الجماعات،
and he agrees to sell me three clubs.
وقد وافق أن يبيعني ثلاث قناني
But in America you have to explain. What are clubs?
في أميريكا، يجب علينا أن نفسر، ما هي هذه القناني؟
Nothing to do with golf.
بالطبع، لا علاقة لها بالجولف
They are those beautiful oblong objects,
إنها هذه الأشياء الرائعة مطاولة الشكل
but quite difficult to make.
وصعبة الصنع في نفس الوقت
They have to be precisely lathed.
يجب ان تكون متناهية الدقة في التوازن
Oh, when I was buying the clubs,
عندما كنت أشتري هذه القناني
somehow the young juggler was hiding from the others.
كان ذلك المتلاعب الشاب يحاول الاختباء من الباقين
Well I didn't think much of it at the time.
لم أمعن التفكير حينها في ذلك الحدث
Anyway, here I was progressing with my new clubs.
على كل، كنت أتمرن على قناني الجديدة
But I could not understand.
ولكني لم أستطع أن أفهم!
I was pretty fast, but I was not fluid at all.
كنت سريعا بما يكفي، ولكن حركتي لم تكن أبدا سلسة
The clubs were escaping me at each throw.
كانت القناني تتفلت مني في كل رمية
And I was trying constantly to bring them back to me.
وكنت أحاول جاهدا أن أعيدها دوما إلي
Until one day I practiced in front of Francis Brunn,
حتى ذلك اليوم حين تدربت أمام فرانسيس برون
the world's greatest juggler.
أشهر المتلاعبين في العالم
And he was frowning.
وقد كان متقطب الوجه من التركيز
And he finally asked, "Can I see those?"
وأخيرا قال: "هل يمكنني رؤيتها؟"
So I proudly showed him my clubs.
وبكل فخر أريته قنانيّ
He said, "Philippe, you have been had.
قال لي: "فيليب، لقد غششت،
These are rejects. They are completely out of alignment.
إنها غير مطابقة للمواصفات، و تخلو من أي انتظام.
They are impossible to juggle."
من المستحيل التلاعب بها."
Tenacity is how I kept at it
الصلابة
against all odds.
هي ما جعلتني أحتفظ بها بالرغم من كل العيوب.
So I went to the circus to see more magicians, more jugglers,
وبعد ذلك ذهبت إلى السيرك كي أرى سحرة ومتلاعبين أكثر
and I saw -- oh no, no, no, I didn't see.
ولقد رأيت، ... كلا، كلا، كلا، لم أر
It was more interesting; I heard.
من الأفضل ان أقول: لقد سمعت
I heard about those amazing men and women
سمعت عن هؤلاء الرجال والنسوة الرائعون
who walk on thin air --
الذين يسيرون على هواء رفيع
the high-wire walkers.
السائرون على الأسلاك المرتفعة
Now I have been playing with ropes and climbing all my childhood,
عبر طفولتي، كنت مغرما باللعب بالحبال والتسلق،
so that's it. I'm 16; I'm becoming a wire walker.
أنا في السادسة عشرة من عمري وسأصبح سائرا على الأسلاك
I found two trees --
وجدت شجرتين
but not any kind of trees,
ولكن ليس أي نوع من الأشجار
trees with character --
أشجار ذات صفة مميزة
and then a very long rope.
وحبل طويل جدا
And I put the rope around and around
لففت الحبل مرة وأخرى وأخرى
and around and around and around till I had no more rope.
وأخرى وأخرى وأخرى حتى لم يعد لدي مزيد من الحبال
Now I have all of those ropes parallel like this.
والآن أصبح لدي كل هذه الحبال متوازية مثل هذا
I get a pair of pliers and some coat hangers,
وأحضرت كماشتين وبضع من الشماعات
and I gather them together in some kind of ropey path.
ومن ثم جمعت هذه الحبال الملفوفة حتى شكلت طريقا حبليا
So I just created the widest tightrope in the world.
وبهذا شكلت أعرض حبل بهلوان مشدود في العالم.
What did I need? I needed the widest shoes in the world.
وماذا احتجت بعد هذه؟ احتجت لأعرض حذاء في العالم
So I found some enormous, ridiculous, giant ski boots
وعندها وجدت أشنع وأسخف وأضخم حذاء للتزلج
and then wobbly, wobbly I get on the ropes.
وعندها، بتهاد صعدت على الحبال
Well within a few days I'm able to do one crossing.
في خلال بضعة أيام استطعت أن أكمل أول عبور
So I cut one rope off.
وعندها قطعت حبلا واحدا
And the next day one rope off.
وفي اليوم التالي، حبل آخر
And a few days later, I was practicing on a single tightrope.
وبعد عدة أيام، كنت أتدرب على حبل واحد فقط
Now you can imagine at that time
يمكنكم أن تتخيلوا تلك الأيام
I had to switch the ridiculous boots for some slippers.
والتي جعلتني أستبدل الحذاء السخيف بخف
So that is how -- in case there are people here in the audience who would like to try --
وتلك كانت الطريقة لمن أراد من الحضور أن يحاول
this is how not to learn wire walking.
كيفية أن يتعلم أن لا يصبح "ماشيا على الحبال"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Intuition is a tool essential in my life.
البداهة هي إحدى الوسائل الأساسية في حياتي.
In the meantime, I am being thrown out of five different schools
في هذه الأثناء، تم طردي من خمس مدارس مختلفة
because instead of listening to the teachers,
وذلك لأني بدلا عن الاستماع للأساتذة
I am my own teacher, progressing in my new art
كنت أستاذ نفسي الخاص، أتقدم في ابداعي الجديد
and becoming a street juggler.
كي أصبح بهلوانا
On the high wire, within months,
فيما يخص المشي على الحبال، وبعد شهور
I'm able to master all the tricks they do in the circus,
استطعت اتقان كل الخدع التي يؤدونها في السيرك
except I am not satisfied.
وبالرغم من ذلك، مازلت لست راضيا
I was starting to invent my own moves and bring them to perfection.
كنت قد بدأت في ابتكار حركاتي الخاصة واتقانها لمرحلة الكمال
But nobody wanted to hire me.
ولكن لم يرغب أي شخص في توظيفي
So I started putting a wire up in secret and performing without permission.
لذا بدأت نصب الحبال بسرية تامة وأداء الحركات دون إذن
Notre Dame,
كنيسة نوتردام
the Sydney Harbor Bridge,
جسر ميناء سيدني
the World Trade Center.
مبنى التجارة العالمي
And I developed a certitude, a faith
وتطور عندي اليقين والإيمان
that convinced me that I will get safely to the other side.
والذي جعلني مقتنعا أني سأصل سالما إلى الجهة المقابلة
If not, I will never do that first step.
لولا ذلك، لم أكن أبدا لأقوم بالخطوة الأولى
Well nonetheless,
ومع ذلك
on the top of the World Trade Center
في أعلى برج التجارة العالمي
my first step was terrifying.
كانت خطوتي الأولى مرعبة
All of a sudden the density of the air is no longer the same.
فجأة وبدون مقدمات تغيرت كثافة الهواء على غير العادة
Manhattan no longer spreads its infinity.
ولم تعد مانهاتن ممتدة كما كانت
The murmur of the city dissolves into a squall
ولاشى الهواء البارد همهمة المدينة
whose chilling power I no longer feel.
ذلك الهواء البارد الذي لم أعد أحس به
I lift the balancing pole. I approach the edge.
رفعت عصا التوازن، وتقدمت نحو الحافة
I step over the beam.
خطوت نحو العارضة
I put my left foot on the cable,
وضعت قدمي اليسرى على الحبل
the weight of my body raised on my right leg
وحملت قدمي اليمنى وزني كله
anchored to the flank of the building.
والتي مازالت مستقرة على طرف المبنى
Shall I ever so slightly shift my weight to the left?
هل يجب على حقا نقل وزني إلى القدم اليسرى؟
My right leg will be unburdened,
وفي لمحة سريعة
my right foot will freely meet the wire.
ستعانق قدمي اليمنى الحبل
On one side, a mass of a mountain, a life I know.
في الطرف الأول، هذه الكتلة الجبلية، حياة أعرفها
On the other, the universe of the clouds,
وفي الطرف الآخر، عالم من السحب
so full of unknown we think it's empty.
مليء بالمجهول، والتي نعتبرها فارغة
At my feet, the path to the north tower -- 60 yards of wire rope.
تحت أقدامي، ممر حبلي بطول 60 ياردة نحو البرج الشمالي
It's a straight line, which sags,
خط مستقيم، متراخي
which sways, which vibrates,
متأرجح، متذبذب
which rolls on itself,
يتمايل حول نفسه
which is ice,
مثلج
which is three tons tight, ready to explode,
ثلاثة أطنان مشدودة، مستعدة للانفجار
ready to swallow me.
مستعدة لابتلاعي
An inner howl assails me,
صوت داخلي هاجمني
the wild longing to flee.
وحرضتني غريزة البقاء على الفرار
But it is too late.
ولكنه جاء متأخرا
The wire is ready.
الحبل مشدود
Decisively my other foot sets itself onto the cable.
على نحو حاسم استقرت قدمي الأخرى على الحبل
Faith is what replaces doubt
اليقين
in my dictionary.
في معجمي هو ما يستبدل الشك
So after the walk
بعد أن قمت بتلك المشية
people ask me, "How can you top that?"
سألني الناس: "كيف أمكنك تحقيق ذلك؟"
Well I didn't have that problem.
حسنا، لم تكن لدي مشكلة
I was not interested in collecting the gigantic,
لم أكن أطمح في أن أكون عملاقا
in breaking records.
ولا أن أحطم الأرقام القياسية
In fact, I put my World Trade Center crossing
في الحقيقة، أنا أعتبر عبور مركز التجارة العالمي
at the same artistic level as some of my smaller walks --
على نفس مستوى الفن الأدائي كسائر مشيي الآخر ولو كان قصيرا
or some completely different type of performance.
أو حتى أدائي لأشياء مختلفة تماما
Let's see, such as my street juggling, for example.
دعونا نرى، كمثال لذلك الحركات البهلوانية التي أؤديها في الشارع
So each time
في كل مرة
I draw my circle of chalk on the pavement
أقوم برسم دائرة على الرصيف بالطبشور
and enter as the improvising comic silent character
وأدخل فيها كالممثل الكوميدي الصامت
I created 45 years ago,
والتي ابتكرتها منذ 45 سنة خلت
I am as happy as when I am in the clouds.
أكون في نفس مستوى السعادة كما لو كنت بين السحاب
But this here,
ولكن هذه هنا
this is not the street.
وهذا ليس الشارع
So I cannot street juggle here, you understand.
وعليه فإنني لا أستطيع أن أؤدي بهلوانيات الشارع
So you don't want me to street juggle here, right?
وأنتم بالتأكيد لا تريدونني أن أعتبر نفسي في الشارع، صحيح؟
You know that, right?
أنتم تعرفون ذلك، صحيح؟
You don't want me to juggle, right?
أنتم لا تريدونني أن أتلاعب، صحيح؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Thank you. Thank you.
شكرا، شكرا
Each time I street juggle
في كل مرة أقوم فيها بالبهلوانيات
I use improvisation.
أستخدم الارتجال
Now improvisation is empowering
الارتجال هو التمكين
because it welcomes the unknown.
لأنه يرحب بالمجهول
And since what's impossible is always unknown,
ولأن المستحيل دوما مجهول
it allows me to believe I can cheat the impossible.
يمنحني الارتجال الثقة أني سأخدع المستحيل
Now I have done the impossible not once,
حتى الآن قد قمت بصنع المستحيل، ليس مرة فقط
but many times.
بل مرات عديدة
So what should I share? Oh, I know. Israel.
إذن، ماذا أشارككم بعد؟ آها، عرفت. إسرائيل
Some years ago I was invited to open the Israel Festival
لعدد من السنين خلت، دعيت لافتتاح مهرجان إسرائيلي
by a high-wire walk.
وذلك بالقيام بمشية على حبل معلق
And I chose to put my wire
واخترت أن أنصب الحبل
between the Arab quarters and the Jewish quarter of Jerusalem
بين الجزء العربي والجزء اليهودي من القدس
over the Ben Hinnom Valley.
فوق وادي بن حنوم
And I thought it would be incredible
واعتقدت أنه بإمكاني أداء فقرة استثنائية
if in the middle of the wire
إذا ما توقفت في منتصف المسافة
I stopped and, like a magician,
وكساحر
I produce a dove and send her in the sky
صنعت حمامة وأرسلتها نحو الفضاء
as a living symbol of peace.
كرمز حي للسلام
Well now I must say,
حسنا، الآن يمكنني القول
it was a little bit hard to find a dove in Israel, but I got one.
أنه كان من الصعوبة أن أجد حمامة في إسرائيل، ولكني فعلت
And in my hotel room,
وفي غرفة الفندق
each time I practiced making it appear and throwing her in the air,
كنت أتدرب مرارا على كيفية جعلها تظهر ومن ثم إرسالها إلى الفضاء
she would graze the wall and end up on the bed.
ولكنها في كل مرة كانت تلمس الحائط وينتهي بها المطاف على السرير
So I said, now it's okay. The room is too small.
وحينها كنت أقول، لا بأس. لابد أن الغرفة صغيرة
I mean, a bird needs space to fly.
أقصد، أن الطيور تحتاج لفضاء رحب كي تطير
It will go perfectly on the day of the walk.
ولكن الأمور ستسير على ما يرام في يوم الحدث الحقيقي
Now comes the day of the walk.
حان اليوم موعد أداء المشية
Eighty thousand people spread over the entire valley.
ثمانون ألف شخص انتشروا على طول الوادي
The mayor of Jerusalem, Teddy Kollek, comes to wish me the best.
وقد حضر عمدة القدس السيد تيدي كوليك متمنيا لي التوفيق
But he seemed nervous.
ولكنه بدا متوترا
There was tension in my wire,
كان الحبل مشدودا
but I also could feel tension on the ground.
ولكني استطعت الاحساس بالتوتر على الأرض أيضا
Because all those people
حيث أن كل هؤلاء الحضور
were made up of people who, for the most part,
كانوا مزيجا من الناس الذين على أغلبهم
considered each other enemies.
يعتبرون أعداء لبعضهم البعض
So I start the walk. Everything is fine.
ومن ثم بدأت المشي، كل شيء وفق الخطة
I stop in the middle.
توقفت في المنتصف
I make the dove appear.
جعلت الحمامة تظهر
People applaud in delight.
صفق الجمهور بهجة
And then in the most magnificent gesture,
وبإيمائة بديعة
I send the bird of peace into the azure.
أطلقت حمامة السلام نحو السماء اللازوردي
But the bird, instead of flying away,
ولكن بدلا عن أن تحلق الحمامة بعيدا
goes flop, flop, flop and lands on my head.
فإذا بها فلوب فلوب فلوب وتحط على يدي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And people scream.
وصرخ الناس
So I grab the dove,
فأمسكت بالحمامة مجددا
and for the second time I send her in the air.
وللمرة الثانية أرسلتها للسماء
But the dove, who obviously didn't go to flying school,
ولكن الحمامة والتي على نحو جلي لم تلتحق بمدرسة تعلم الطيران
goes flop, flop, flop and ends up at the end of my balancing pole.
تعاود الكرة، فلوب فلوب فلوب وينتهي بها المطاف على طرف عصا التوازن
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You laugh, you laugh. But hey.
تضحكون، تضحكون، ولكن
I sit down immediately. It's a reflex of wire walkers.
جلست بعد ذلك مباشرة، إنه رد فعل طبيعي لكل السائرين على الحبال
Now in the meantime, the audience, they go crazy.
في هذه الأثناء،اشتدت حماسة كل الحضور
They must think this guy with this dove,
لابد أنهم اعتقدوا أن هذا الرجل وهذه الحمامة
he must have spent years working with him.
قد قضوا سنينا يعملون مع بعضهم
What a genius, what a professional.
يا للعبقرية، وياللاحترافية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I take a bow. I salute with my hand.
لذا فقد انحنيت لهم، وحييتهم بيدي
And at the end I bang my hand against the pole
وفي النهاية، خبطت بيدي العصا
to dislodge the bird.
كيما أزيح الحمامة عنها
Now the dove, who, now you know, obviously cannot fly,
الآن، مع هذه الحمامة التي أصبحتم تعرفون جليا عدم قدرتها على الطيران
does for the third time a little flop, flop, flop
قامت للمرة الثالثة، فلوب فلوب فلوب
and ends up on the wire behind me.
وانتهى بها المطاف على الحبل في الجانب الخلفي لي
And the entire valley goes crazy.
وشعر كل الجمهور في الوادي بالحماسة
Now but hold on, I'm not finished.
وأخيرا، ولكن القصة لم تنتهي
So now I'm like 50 yards from my arrival
هأنذا على بعد 50 ياردة تقريبا من الوصول
and I'm exhausted, so my steps are slow.
وقد أصابني الإعياء، وتثاقلت خطواتي
And something happened.
وفجأة، حدث شيء ما
Somebody somewhere, a group of people,
شخص ما، في مكان ما، مجموعة من الأشخاص
starts clapping in rhythm with my steps.
بدأوا في التصفيق بالتزامن مع خطواتي
And within seconds the entire valley
وفي غضون ثوان، كل الوادي
is applauding in unison with each of my steps.
أصبح يصفق في انسجام مع كل خطوة أخطوها
But not an applause of delight like before,
ولكنه ليس تصفيق ابتهاج كما كان سابقا
an applause encouragement.
لقد كان تشجيعيا هذه المرة
For a moment, the entire crowd had forgotten their differences.
للحظة، تناست الحشود جميع الفوارق بينها
They had become one, pushing me to triumph.
لقد أصبحوا واحدا، يدفعونني نحو النصر
I want you just for a second
أريد منكم للحظات فقط
to experience this amazing human symphony.
أن تجربوا هذه السيمفونية الإنسانية الرائعة
So let's say I am here and the chair is my arrival.
لذا تصوروا معي أني هنا، وذلك الكرسي هو نقطة وصولي
So I walk, you clap, everybody in unison.
حينما أخطو، تصفقوا، كلكم في انسجام
(Clapping)
(صفقة)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So after the walk, Teddy and I become friends.
بعد هذه المشية، أصبحنا أنا وتيدي أصدقاء
And he tells me, he has on his desk a picture of me
وقد أخبرني أنه يحتفظ لي بصورة في مكتبه
in the middle of the wire with a dove on my head.
حينما كنت في وسط الحبل والحمامة في يدي
He didn't know the true story.
ولكنه لم يكن يعلم القصة الحقيقية
And whenever he's daunted by an impossible situation
لقد أصبح تيدي كلما أصابته الهيبة من موقف مستعص
to solve in this hard-to-manage city,
على الحل في هذه المدينة التي تصعب إدارتها
instead of giving up, he looks at the picture and he says,
وبدلا عن الاستسلام فإنه يلقي نظرة على الصورة ويقول
"If Philippe can do that, I can do this,"
"إذا كان باستطاعة فيليب أن يقوم بذلك، فباستطاعتي القيام بهذا"
and he goes back to work.
ويعود مجددا لاستكمال عمله
Inspiration.
الإلهام
By inspiring ourselves
بإلهام أنفسنا
we inspire others.
نلهم الآخرين
I will never forget this music,
لن أنسى أبدا هذه الموسيقى
and I hope now neither will you.
وأتمنى أن لا ينساها أحدكم
Please take this music with you home,
رجاء، فلتحملوا هذه الموسيقى معكم إلى بيوتكم
and start gluing feathers to your arms
وابدأوا بإلصاق الريش إلى أذرعكم
and take off and fly,
ومن ثم حلقوا
and look at the world from a different perspective.
وانظروا إلى العالم من منظور مختلف
And when you see mountains,
وعندما ترون الجبال
remember mountains can be moved.
تذكروا أن الجبال يمكن أن تحرك
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. Thank you.
شكرا، شكرا
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)